Guide to the Nell Irvin Painter Papers, 1793-2021 and undated, bulk 1876-2007 RL.00990
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Writings and Research Series, 1793, 1835-2007 and undated, bulk 1876-2004, 66 boxes
  - Standing at Armageddon Subseries, 1851-1999 and undated, bulk 1882-1913 and 1971-1988, 11 boxes
    Consists of correspondence, drafts, related talks and writings, and extensive research materials related to Painter's work on Standing at Armageddon: The United States, 1877-1919 (1987). Divided into Correspondence, Drafts, and Research Materials subgroups.
    Compared to other subseries, the Standing at Armageddon Subseries contains relatively little correspondence. The existing materials are largely publication-related. The correspondence with the Henry George School of Social Science includes a lesson plan and quiz questions on Standing at Armageddon. Related correspondence perhaps may be found in the Correspondence Series. The Drafts subgroup includes a manuscript, several typescripts, and two master proofs. The Research subgroup materials include photocopies of scholarly articles, newspaper articles, and Congressional records, as well as extensive notes from those materials and books. The subgroup also includes talks, reviews, and articles by Painter.
    In addition to materials directly about the book, all materials in the Writings and Research Series involving the issues of labor, gender, and race, as they relate to the economic and political conditions of the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, have been incorporated into the Standing at Armageddon Subseries. The subseries also includes materials on the South that are relevant to the period addressed by Standing at Armageddon.
    The correspondence and research materials are arranged alphabetically, while the drafts are arranged chronologically. Talks or articles by Painter have generally been identified by (NIP) following the work's title. As three typescripts of Standing at Armageddon lack any date information, they have been labeled A to C. This labeling does not reflect any chronological ordering among those typescripts. In addition, inasmuch as their dating is uncertain, those typescripts have been placed after the other typescripts in the subseries.
    - Correspondence (Box 114)
      - Borland, Bruce: Harper Collins, 1995 (Box 114)
      - Henry George School of Social Science, 1997 (Box 114)
      - Kehoe, Bob (W.W. Norton & Co.), 1987 (Box 114)
      - Kelley, Mary: 1986 (Box 114)
      - Zeidel, 1999 Oct. 5 (Box 114)
    - Drafts
      - Circa 1985, Chapters 1-2, 3 folders (Box 114)
      - Circa 1985-1986, edited typescript, Folder 1 of 4 (Box 114)
      - Circa 1985-1986, edited typescript, Folders 2-4 of 4 (Box 115)
      - 1986
        - June, typescript, 3 folders (Box 115)
        - Sept.-Oct., copy-edited typescript, Folders 1-4 of10 (Box 115)
        - Sept.-Oct., copy-edited typescript, Folders 5-10 of 10 (Box 116)
      - Circa 1986
        - Introduction, manuscript (Box 116)
        - Introduction, USA at Turn of 20th Century (Box 116)
        - Typescript A, Folders 1-2 of 3 (Box 116)
        - Typescript A, Folder 3 of 3 (Box 117)
        - Typescript B, 5 folders (Box 117)
        - Typescript C, 4 folders (Box 117)
      - 1987 (Box 118)
        - Apr., master proof, 3 folders (Box 118)
        - June, draft of "Index" (Box 118)
        - June, master proof, 3 folders (Box 118)
    - Research Materials
      - 1919, Frederick Howe: Confessions of a Reformer, 1967, notes, circa 1984 (Box 118)
      - 1975 and undated (Box 118)
      - American Association Labor Legislation pamphlets, undated (Box 118)
      - American Nonconformist, notes, circa 1984 (Box 118)
      - Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1906, notes, circa 1984 (Box 118)
      - Appeal to Reason (Girard, Kansas), undated, notes, circa 1984 (Box 118)
      - The Arena, 1891-1898, notes, circa 1984 (Box 118)
      - Armes, Ethel: Story of Coal and Iron in Alabama, 1910 (Box 118)
      - Atlanta Constitution, 1884-1886, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - Atlanta Constitution, 1891-1892, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - Bagby, Wesley M.: Presidential campaign of 1920, 1962, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - Bailey, Thomas A.: Wilson and the Peacemakers, 1944, 1945, and 1947, notes, circa 1984 (Box 119)
      - Baker, Ray Stannard: American Chronicle, 1945 (on 1919 and later), notes, undated, [Mold identified and remediated.] (Box 119)
      - Baker, Ray Stannard: Our New Prosperity, 1900, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - Ballinger Case, 1910 (Box 119)
      - Ballinger-Pinchot Controversy, 1910 (Box 119)
      - Beer, Thomas: Hanna, N.Y., Knopf, 1929, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - Bellamy, Edward: Looking Backward, 1888, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - Black women's organizations, 1977 (Box 119)
      - Bloor, Ella Reeve: We Are Many, 1940, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - Blumberg, Dorothy Rose: Florence Kelley, 1966, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - Blum, John Morton: The Progressive Presidents, New York, 1980, notes, circa 1984 (Box 119)
      - Bruce, Robert: 1877: Year of Violence, 1970, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - Bryan, William: The Commoner, 1901-1903, notes, circa 1984 (Box 119)
      - Bryan, William, et al: Republic or Empire, 1899, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - Buchanan, Joseph R.: The Story of A Labor Agitator, 1903, notes, circa 1984 (Box 119)
      - Buder, Stanley: Pullman, 1967, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - Bureau of Labor Statistics, 1985 (Box 119)
      - Carnegie, Andrew: Gospel of Wealth, etc., notes, undated (Box 119)
      - The Century, 1982 July, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - Charles W. Dabney Papers, Southern Historical Collection, UNC-Chapel Hill, notes, circa 1984 (Box 119)
      - Chicago Inter-Ocean, 1892, notes, circa 1984 (Box 119)
      - The Chicago Record on the Wilmington Riot of 1898, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - Chicago Tribune, Philadelphia Christian Recorder, 1882-1885 (Box 119)
      - Clark, Thomas D., ed.: Travels in the New South, 1962, 2 vols., notes, circa 1984 (Box 119)
      - Cleveland, Grover: Annual address, 1886 ( New York Times), notes, undated, [Mold identified and remediated.] (Box 119)
      - Coben, Stanley: A. Mitchell Palmer: Politician, 1963, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - Cooper, John Milton, Jr.: The Vanity of Power, 1969, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - Cooper, John: On World War I, 1980-1981 (Box 119)
      - Cott, Nancy, and N. S. Dye: 1986, 2 writings (Box 119)
      - Croly, Herbert, and Marcus Alonzo Hanna: 1912, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - Currency, Banking, and the Federal Reserve System, notes, circa 1984 (Box 119)
      - Cutler, John Henry: Honey Fitz... John F. (Honey Fitz) Fitzgerald, 1962, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - Daniel Augustus Tompkins Papers (1851-1914), Southern Historical Collection, UNC-Chapel Hill, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - Daniels, Jonathan: The End of Innocence, 1954, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - Daniels, Josephus: Editor in Politics, 1941, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - Daniels, Josephus: Tar Heel Editor, 1939, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - Davis, Allen F.: American Heroine, 1973, notes, circa 1984 (Box 119)
      - Douglas, F.: on Paris Commune, 1871, notes, circa 1984 (Box 119)
      - Dye, Nancy Schrom: As Equals and as Sisters:... WTVL of New York, 1980 (Box 119)
      - The Election of 1980 and Afro-Americans--Historical Aspects, undated (Box 119)
      - Emancipation in Black and White, (NIP), Millersville University, Meaning of Emancipation, 1990 (Box 119)
      - Emerson Essays, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - The Federal Reserve Act, notes, circa 1984 (Box 119)
      - Fields, Mamie Garvin: On Crackers and White People, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - Filene, Peter G.: Americans and the Soviet Experiment, 1917-1933, 1967, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - Fink, Leon, Workingmen's Democracy, 1983 (Box 119)
      - Flexner, Eleanor: Century of Struggle, 1959, 1975, notes, circa 1984 (Box 119)
      - The Forum, notes, undated (Box 119)
      - Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper and Harper's Weekly, 1883-1884, notes, circa 1984 (Box 119)
      - Frederickson, Mary: Theory and Practice in Southern Textile Organizing, 1985, [Mold identified and remediated.] (Box 120)
      - Friedman, Milton: Monetary History, 1963, notes, undated; Historical Statistics of the United States, 1975 (Box 120)
      - Front Matter, 1970, 1975, 1982, and undated (Box 120)
      - Fussell, Paul: The Great War and Modern Memory, N.Y., OUP, 1975, notes, undated (Box 120)
      - Garland, Hamlin: A Son of the Middle Border, 1917, notes, undated (Box 120)
      - Garland, Hamlin: A Spoil of Office, 1897, notes, undated (Box 120)
      - Gatewood, Willard B., Jr.: Black Americans and the White Man's Burden, 1975, notes, undated (Box 120)
      - George, Henry: Progress and Poverty, 1879, notes, circa 1984 (Box 120)
      - Gilbert, James: Designing the Industrial State, 1972, notes, circa 1984 (Box 120)
      - Goodwyn, Lawrence: Democratic Promise, 1976, notes, undated (Box 120)
      - Greeley, Andrew M.: That Most Distressful Nation, 1972 (Box 120)
      - Green, Dan S. and Earl Smith: W.E.B. Dubois and the Concepts of Race and Class, 1983 (Box 120)
      - Historical Statistics of the U.S., undated (Box 120)
      - Hoover, Herbert: The Ordeal of Woodrow Wilson, 1958, notes, undated (Box 120)
      - House Report 4174, Labor Troubles in the South and West, 1887 (Box 120)
      - Hunter College, (NIP), 1986 May 7 (Box 120)
      - James, Edward: Notable American Women, 1971 (Box 120)
      - Johns Hopkins Labor Seminar, papers, 1984 Apr. (Box 120)
      - Johns Hopkins Labor Seminar, papers and correspondence, 1984 Apr. (Box 120)
      - John Swinton's Paper, notes, circa 1984 (Box 120)
      - Kann, Kenneth: Knights of Labor and the Southern Black Worker, Labor History, 1977 (Box 120)
      - Kellogg, Charles Flint: NAACP, 1967, notes, undated (Box 120)
      - Kessler-Harris, Alice, Out to Work, 1982, notes, undated (Box 120)
      - Kipling, Rudyard: American Notes, New York, Frank F. Lovell Co., 1889 (Box 120)
      - Koskoff, David E.: Joseph P. Kennedy, A Life and Times, 1974, notes, undated (Box 120)
      - Labor Troubles, House of Representatives, 1987 (Box 120)
      - Lagemann, Ellen Condliffe: A Generation of Women, 1979 (Box 120)
      - The Lawrence Strike, photocopies, 1912, and notes, circa 1984, 2 folders (Box 120)
      - Levine, Edward M.: The Irish and Irish Politicians, 1966 (Box 120)
      - Lewis, David and Arnold Rampersad on the Black Left, 1987 (Box 120)
      - Lipset, Seymour Martin: Party Coalitions in the 1980s, 1981, notes, undated (Box 120)
      - The Living of Charlotte Perkins Gilman, 1935, notes, circa 1984 (Box 120)
      - Marion Butler Papers, Southern Historical Collection, UNC-Chapel Hill, notes, circa 1984, 3 folders (Box 121)
      - Marks, Carole: Split Labor Markets and Black-White Relations, 1865-1920, 1981 (Box 121)
      - Mayer, Arno J.: Politics and Diplomacy of Peacemaking, 1967, notes, undated (Box 121)
      - McClure's Magazine, 1893-1894, notes, circa 1984 (Box 121)
      - Mindel, Jacob: 1953, notes, undated (Box 121)
      - Monkkonen, Eric: Police in Urban America, 1860-1920, 1981 (Box 121)
      - Montgomery, David, New Tendencies in Union Struggles, Labor in the Republics, and NEH application, J. Carroll Moody, undated, 1980, and 1983 (Box 121)
      - Montgomery, David: The 'New Unionism' and the Transformation of Workers' Consciousness in America, 1909-1922, 1974 (Box 121)
      - Montgomery Review, Labor history, (NIP), 1988 (Box 121)
      - Murray, Robert K.: Red Scare, 1955, notes, circa 1984 (Box 121)
      - The Nation, 1877; The International Review, 1877; Radical Review, 1877; International Review, 1877 (Box 121)
      - The Nation, 108, 109, 1919 Jan.-1919 Dec., notes, circa 1984 (Box 121)
      - Nelson, Bruce: 1986 (Box 121)
      - The New York Globe-Free Man, 1883-1885, notes, circa 1984 (Box 121)
      - New York Times, 1884, and notes, circa 1984 (Box 121)
      - Noer, Thomas J.: Briton, Boer, and Yankee, 1978 (Box 121)
      - Noggle, Burl: Into the Twenties: The U.S. from Armistice to Normalcy, 1974, notes, 1984 (Box 121)
      - Norrell, Jeff: Caste in Steel, 1985 (Box 121)
      - Northrup, Herbert: Negro Employment in Basic Industry, 1970 (Box 121)
      - Notes, circa 1984, 5 folders (Box 121)
      - Notes and photocopies, undated (Box 122)
      - O'Neill, William L.: The Woman Movement, 1969, notes, circa 1984 (Box 122)
      - One or Two Things About The Fall of the House of Labor, (NIP), 1989 (Box 122)
      - Ovington, Mary White: The Walls Came Tumbling Down, 1947, notes, undated (Box 122)
      - Painter: Immigration charts and figures, 1984 and undated (Box 122)
      - Painter, Nell Irvin: Black workers from agriculture to industry, 1983 (Box 122)
      - Painter, Nell Irvin: Black workers... from Reconstruction to... Depression, 1980 (Box 122)
      - Paris Commune and 1877 strikes, New York Public Library, notes, circa 1984 (Box 122)
      - Paul, Arnold M.: Conservative Crisis and the Rule of Law, 1960, notes, undated (Box 122)
      - Pennsylvania Historical Society, 1873-1876, notes, undated (Box 122)
      - Periodicals, 1898-1905 (Box 122)
      - Phillips, David Graham: 1905, notes, undated (Box 122)
      - A Post Energy Crisis History of the U.S. at the Turn of the 20th Century, (NIP), 1982 Oct. (Box 122)
      - A Post Energy History of the U.S... ., (NIP), Social Science Newsletter, 1983 (Box 122)
      - Price, Bradley R.: Progressive Cities, 1977, notes, undated (Box 122)
      - Primary sources, Chapter 5, undated (Box 122)
      - Pujo Committee, 1912-1913 (Box 122)
      - Race riots in Atlanta, 1906, and Springfield, Illinois, 1908, 2 folders (Box 122)
      - Ratner, Sidney: The Tariff in American History, 1972 (Box 122)
      - Report of U.S. Industrial Commission, Trusts, pt. 1, 1900 (Box 122)
      - Response to 'Myth-Making as Labor History: Herbert Gutman...,' (NIP), circa 1988 (Box 123)
      - Review of Terminal Visions for The Nation, (NIP), 1983 (Box 123)
      - Riley, B.F.: The White Man's Burden, 1910, notes, circa 1984 (Box 123)
      - Rogers, Daniel T: In Search of Progressivism, Reviews in American History, 1982 (Box 123)
      - Rogers, William W.: The One-Gallused Rebellion, 1970, notes, undated (Box 123)
      - Roosevelt, Theodore: Armageddon Speech, 1912, notes, circa 1984 (Box 123)
      - Roosevelt, Theodore: The New Nationalism, 1910, notes, circa 1984 (Box 123)
      - Russell, Charles Edward: Bare Hands and Stone Walls, 1933, notes, undated (Box 123)
      - Russell, Charles Edward: The Story of the Nonpartisan League, 1920, notes, undated (Box 123)
      - Russell, Francis: A City in Terror, 1975, notes, circa 1984 (Box 123)
      - Semonche, John E.: Charting the Future, 1978, notes, undated (Box 123)
      - Senate Committee on relations between labor and capital, 1885, notes, circa 1984 (Box 123)
      - Senate hearings on labor and capital, vols. 1, 2, and 4, 1885, 2 folders (Box 123)
      - Shannon, David A., ed.: Beatrice Webb's American Diary, 1898, Madison, University of Wisconsin Press, 1963 (Box 123)
      - Shannon, William V.: The American Irish, 1963 (Box 123)
      - Sherman, John: John Sherman's Recollections, 1895, notes, circa 1984 (Box 123)
      - The Shirtwaist Maker's Strike, 1909 Nov.-1910 Feb. (Box 123)
      - Social History Project, Graduate Center, CUNY, 1985 Nov. (Box 123)
      - Socialism, 1911-1913 (Box 123)
      - Soule, George: Prosperity Decade: From War to Depression, 1947, notes, circa 1984 (Box 123)
      - Southern Black Industrial Workers in the Twentieth Century.. ., (NIP), German-American Symposium on workers, 1984, 3 folders (Box 123)
      - Southern Black Industrial Workers.. ., (NIP), circa 1985 (Box 123)
      - Southern Educational Board Papers, Southern Historical Collection, UNC-Chapel Hill, notes, circa 1984, 2 folders (Box 123)
      - Stephenson, Nathaniel W., Nelson M. Aldrich and notes, undated (Box 123)
      - Strong, Josiah: Our Country, 1885 (Box 123)
      - The Survey, 1919; notes, circa 1984 (Box 124)
      - Tarbell, Ida: All in the Day's Work: An Autobiography, 1939, notes, circa 1984 (Box 124)
      - Tarbell, Ida M.: All in the Day's Work, 1939, notes, undated (Box 124)
      - Tax, Meredith: Rising of the Women.. ., 1980, notes, circa 1984 (Box 124)
      - Thomas E. Watson Papers, Southern Historical Collection, Wilson Library, UNC-Chapel Hill, notes, circa 1984 (Box 124)
      - Thornbrough, Emma Lou: T. Thomas Fortune, 1972, notes, circa 1984 (Box 124)
      - Tindall, George: A Populist Reader, 1966, notes, undated (Box 124)
      - U.S. at turn of the century, (NIP), undated (Box 124)
      - U.S. economic and social history (1890s), notes, undated (Box 124)
      - Vanderblue, Homer, and William Crum: Iron Industry in Prosperity and Depression, 1927 (Box 124)
      - Villard, Oswald Garrison: Fighting Years, 1939, notes, circa 1984 (Box 124)
      - Vorse, Mary Heaton: A Footnote to Folly, 1935, notes, undated (Box 124)
      - Weinstein, James: The Decline of Socialism in America, 1912-1917, 1962, notes, circa 1984 (Box 124)
      - Wertheimer, Barbara: We Were There, 1977 (Box 124)
      - Whalen, Richard J.: The Founding Father, The Story of Joseph P. Kennedy, 1964, notes, circa 1984 (Box 124)
      - White, Walter: A Man Called White, 1948 (Box 124)
      - White, William Allen
        - Autobiography, 1910-1912 section, 1946, notes, circa 1984 (Box 124)
        - Autobiography, 1946, notes, circa 1984 (Box 124)
        - Maverick on Main Street, John DeWitt McKee, 1975, notes, circa 1984 (Box 124)
      - Wiebe, Robert H: The Search for Order, 1877-1920, notes, circa 1984 (Box 124)
      - Wolfe, Bertram D.: A Life in Two Centuries, 1981, notes, circa 1984 (Box 124)
      - Wood, Major General Leonard, circa 1984 (Box 124)
      - Wooley, Robert H.: Race and Politics: Evolution of the White Supremacy Campaign of 1898 in N.C., 1977, UNC dissertation, notes, circa 1984 (Box 124)
      - Wool tariff, (Jere Link), 1908-1909 and 1982 (Box 124)
  - Other Research Topics Subseries, 1793, 1847-2007 and undated, bulk 1975-2002, 22 boxes
    Consists of eleven subgroups: Black Nationalism, Civil Rights, Civil War, Ella Thomas, Gender and Sexuality, Historiography, Other Materials, Photography, Religion, Southern History (which includes a folder grouping on Reconstruction), and Walter White. The materials contained within these subgroups include photocopies of and notes from books and articles, as well as drafts of Painter's writings. Some related correspondence, as well as three fictional works of unknown origin, are also included. The materials in this subseries have been organized alphabetically.
    - Black Nationalism (Box 125)
      Consists of materials on Martin Delany and on the various representations of Malcolm X.
      - Delany, Martin R.: Black Abolitionists, notes, circa 1981 (Box 125)
      - Delany, Martin R.: Official Report of the Niger Valley Exploring Party, 1860, notes, circa 1985 (Box 125)
      - Delany Freedom History Project and National Archives, 1983-1984 and undated (Box 125)
      - Delany from Contway Library, Harvard Medical School, and Reg Hildebrand's Pages, 1983 and undated (Box 125)
      - Martin Delany, (NIP), 1985-1987 (Box 125)
      - Martin Delany, (NIP), American Historical Association, 1986 (Box 125)
      - Martin Delany and the End of Reconstruction: Race, Class, and Nationalism, (NIP), 1985 Jan.-Feb. (Box 125)
      - Martin Delany, a Black Nationalist in Two Kinds of Time, (NIP), 1986 (Box 125)
      - Martin Delany in Two Kinds of Time, (NIP), American Historical Association, Chicago, 1986 (Box 125)
      - Martin Delany, Wade Hampton III, and the End of Reconstruction, (NIP), 1986 (Box 125)
      - Martin Delany and Wade Hampton III, South Carolina State Archives, photocopies and notes, undated (Box 125)
      - Martin Delany with citations, draft, (NIP), circa 1985 (Box 125)
      - Martin R. Delany: Elitism and Black Nationalism, (NIP), 1985, 3 folders (Box 125)
      - Martin R. Delany, South Carolina, 1876 (Box 125)
      - Malcolm X Across the Genres, (NIP)--drafts, proofs, and offprints from American Historical Review, 1992-1993, Folders 1-2 of 6 (Box 125)
      - Malcolm X Across the Genres, (NIP)--drafts, proofs, and offprints from American Historical Review, 1992-1993, Folders 3-6 of 6 (Box 126)
    - Civil Rights
      Contains drafts and research materials on affirmative action, Jim Crow, the Equal Rights Amendment, Anita Hill and Lani Guinier, and voter fraud.
      - Affirmative action, 1981, 1995-1996 (Box 126)
      - Affirmative Action, (NIP), University of Virginia, 1981 (Box 126)
      - Bell, Derrick, 1986 (Box 126)
      - Brown v. Board of Education, the Cold War and White Suburbanization, (NIP) 2003 (Box 126)
      - Guinier, Lani, from the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, 1993 (Box 126)
      - Hers, on affirmative action, (NIP), 1981 (Box 126)
      - Hill, Anita and Lani Guinier, 1993 May 24 (Box 126)
      - Jack Johnson, the ERA and Boley, Oklahoma, 1975 (Box 126)
      - Jim Crow at Harvard: 1923, (NIP), circa 1971 (Box 126)
      - Law articles on affirmative action and civil rights, 1984 and 1988, 2 writings (Box 126)
      - New York Council for the Humanities, (NIP) 1987 May 15 (Box 126)
      - Race Relations, History and Public Policy: The Alabama Vote Fraud Cases of 1985, (NIP), 1987 (Box 126)
      - Perspectives, (NIP), 1993 Dec. (Box 126)
      - Report to the Committee to Review Affirmative Action, Harvard University, 1989 (Box 126)
      - Review of A Life in the Struggle, (NIP), 1989 (Box 126)
      - Trenton Times on affirmative action, (NIP), 1995 Apr. (Box 126)
      - Voting Rights Act, 1988 July 15 (Box 126)
      - Woodward, C. Vann: The Strange Career of Jim Crow, 1955 (Box 126)
    - Civil War and Antebellum Period
      Beside materials on the Civil War, subgroup also includes materials on Frederick Douglass, slavery, and the Antebellum Period. Among the article drafts and research materials, the subgroup contains several photocopies of photographs.
      - Bet testimony, 1793 (Box 126)
      - Did the South Lose the Civil War? (NIP), 1991 (Box 126)
      - Goodman, Paul: White over White: Planters, Yeoman, and the Coming of Civil War, 1980 (Box 126)
      - Honest Abe and Uncle Tom, (NIP), 2000-2001, 2 folders (Box 126)
      - McPherson, James M.: Drawn with the Sword, 1996 (Box 126)
      - Photographs, New York Public Library, undated (Box 126)
      - Poor Black Women and Rich White Women in the Antebellum U.S. South..., (NIP), Berkshire Conference, 1990 (Box 127)
      - Review of Frederick Douglass, (NIP), 1990 (Box 127)
      - Review of Ira Berlin, Many Thousands Gone, (NIP), African American Review, 1999 (Box 127)
      - Review of Waldo Martin, The Mind of Frederick Douglass, (NIP), In These Times, 1985 May (Box 127)
      - Spivey Review of Frederick Douglass by W. S. McFeely, 1993 (Box 127)
      - Stuckey, Sterling: Babo--The Negro as Hero, 1980 (Box 127)
      - VLS review of Arguing About Slavery, 1995 (Box 127)
    - Ella Thomas
      Painter wrote the introduction for The Secret Eye: The Journal of Ella Gertrude Clanton Thomas, 1848-1889, which was edited by Virginia Burr. The Ella Thomas subgroup contains correspondence with Virginia Burr, book covers, typescripts of the diary, and typescripts and printer's proofs of the book.
      - Book covers, 1995 (Box 127)
      - Bryant, Jonathan: The Work of Negroes and Thieves: Georgia's Homestead and Exemption Laws, 1868-1877, 1988 (Box 127)
      - Burr, Virginia, correspondence, 1988-1989, 2 folders (Box 127)